RICHARD J. NUGENT III

365 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY 10016

(847) 736-2597 \$\phi\$ richard.nugent.3@gmail.com \$\phi\$ sites.google.com/view/richardnugent

PROFILE

My dissertation documents the economic consequences of barriers to international capital markets. The methods involved in my research include panel data analysis using fixed effects, instrumental variables, and Arellano-Bond GMM. I also use quasi-experimental methods including the synthetic control method, difference-in-difference, and elastic net regularization as an effective solution to the endogeneity problem. I find new evidence that barriers to international capital markets can have unintended consequences for international lending and private credit.

EDUCATION

The Graduate Center, City University of New York, New York, NY

Ph.D., Economics, Expected May 2019

M.A., Economics, May 2018

Specializations: Financial Economics, Public Finance, Applied Econometrics

Select Coursework: Quantitative Macroeconomics, Macroeconometrics, Corporate Finance, Big Data Analytics

The University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago, IL

B.A., Economics, May 2012

Chicago Civic Leadership Certificate, May 2010

SKILLS

Modeling Generalized Linear Models, Panel Data, Time Series, Potential Outcomes (DiD, Elastic

Net, Multivariate Matching, Propensity Score, SCM), Partial Equilibrium Simulation

Programming GAMS, MATLAB, Python, R, SQL.

Software & Tools Eviews, LATEX, Mathematica, MS Office Suite, Stata, Tableau.

Languages English (Native), Spanish (Fully Proficient).

EXPERIENCE

Department of Economics, Hunter College, CUNY, New York, NY

Adjunct Lecturer, January 2014 - Present

- · Taught a large portfolio of economics courses to over 1300 Hunter College students over six years.
- · Tasked with teaching large format sections (enrollment of up to 140 students), requiring extensive use of Microsoft PowerPoint in the design of digital assets.

Office of Economics, US International Trade Commission, Washington DC

Economist Trainee, June 2017 - August 2017/May 2018 - August 2018

- · Used matching econometrics to analyze the influence of non-tariff measures on international trade using Python.
- · Simulated industry-specific economic shocks using a partial equilibrium Armington framework in the steel and coal industries using the General Algebraic Modeling System (**GAMS**) software.
- · Published a comprehensive literature review on measures of trade in value-added and their policy implications in USITC Economics Working Paper "An Overview on the Construction of the North American Regional Supply-Use and Input-Output Tables and their Applications in Policy Analysis."
- · Collected, cleaned, and organized large data sets in **Stata** for use in regression analysis.

Economic Studies Group (ESG), New York, NY

Advanced Research Collaborative Fellow, Contributor, August 2017 - August 2018

- · Published a primer on the role that rules of origin played in the renegotiation of NAFTA (USMCA).
- · Contributed to ESG policy analyses by generating original data visualization using R.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

"Restrictions on Short-term Capital Inflows and the Response of Direct Investment" (Forthcoming) Eastern Economic Journal, 2018.

ACADEMIC AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Provost's Office University Fellowship (2018), Teaching and Learning Center Mini Grant (2017), Advanced Research Collaborative Fellowship (2017), Sallie Mae Student Fellowship Award (2015)